dr. Chuck Chakrapani is something of a
Renaissance man so he's a local
Torontonian and he's a psychologist by
training but a data scientist by
profession and he's the president of I
think Canada's largest independent
market research firm he's written over
20 books one of them which you may have
heard of called unshakeable freedom
ancient stoic secrets applied to modern
life today his talk is on his
forthcoming book how to be stoic when
you don't know how and this talk is
right at the center of the bullseye in
terms of our theme for the day which is
practice I'm really excited to invite
Chuck he's going to talk about theory of
stoicism but specifically mental
exercises that you can use to train
these stoic theories into practice and
bring into your life so will you join me
in welcoming dr. Chuck Chakrapani to the
stage how to be a stoic when you don't
know how what do you do this what I do I
go to the library start reading
it's okay for a while it goes well and
then you find there are so many concepts
concept of the concepts or the concepts
of content and so little time so you
start like that and end like this now
the fact is the stoicism to understand
the basics it's very simple it doesn't
have to be complicated in fact think of
stoicism as a symphony okay choices are
made Symphony if you go to a symphony
for the full Symphony Orchestra consists
of hundred musicians or more and yet if
you observe closely about a third of
them are playing just one instrument
violin and two-thirds of the orchestras
playing just four instruments and 93% or
playing only eight instruments so even
though it looks chaotic even though
there are hundred musicians they are
just playing eight instruments story
system it's very much like that the
basic concepts are few there are many
variations you can go into depth but the
basic concepts of you what's the purpose
of Stoicism it has only one purpose to
make you happy to let you have a good
life okay that that's the purpose of
choices and it's your demonic philosophy
see how to be happy okay and it also
says what is that raw material you have
what the raw material which you can use
to make yourself happy or to have the
good life
it says the raw material you have is
what they call impressions if you are
hungry that's an impression if you think
the room is too cold
that's an impression if we think the
room is too warm it's the innocent
impression if you think your life is
going nowhere that's an impression all
these sort impressions
some of these impressions are true some
are false so how do you take these
impressions and convert this into you
into your ammonia or the good life that
is the basic challenge of stoicism okay
what they say is to do that you need for
special skills they are wisdom justice
moderation and courage and you need to
practice three disciplines the
discipline opposite and the discipline
of desire and the discipline of action
if only you could do that
take your judgments and use these skills
and use these disciplines you will have
a good life this is the basis of
stoicism okay so you have all you have
in life are impressions think about it
everything is an impression you lose
your job that's an impression the doctor
says your cancer that's an impression
how do you take all these impressions
and have a good life so
the way I'm going to explain this he's
using metaphor of a house if you look at
a house
it has foundation going in four
directions but it is four walls and it
has three windows idea oops
stopping in two directions keep this in
mind so think of it has stoicism okay
what are the foundations what are the
walls what are the windows
what's the roof okay that's what we're
going to be talking about let's start
with the foundations its foundations of
stoicism want these there are what is
happiness meet whatever the SAP does
mean to you what's the good life meet to
you anybody want to tell me what good
life means to them oh you want me to
tell you okay there are many things you
know for if you are in sub-saharan
Africa and then you want to have if you
don't have any meals your next meal is
your happiness yeah if you are in
subsistence economy if your three meals
today that's happiness if you are a
millionaire in New York maybe a billion
would make you happy if you are like me
a good meal and a cigar would is the
definition of happiness so happiness
depends on who you ask
but xeno the founder of stoicism had a
very very neat definition he said
happiness is a life that flows smoothly
think about it happiness it's a life
that flows smoothly that means if you
look at the birds or any bird
it likes what is our life our life will
have full of problem
and I really want to scratch the surface
right
to us why do we have all these problems
why can't we glide like a bird in the
sky okay
and the strike said you have all these
problems because you don't live with it
in accordance with nature you have all
this problems because you don't live in
accordance with nature
big deal I don't you know what living
accounts in the chalice to nature mean
so what does it mean listen you won't
know what it means it's kind of
confusing isn't it living in accordance
with nature it looks kind of fancy you
know it looks it says something but what
does it say how do you live in
accordance with nature
stoic said live in accordance with
nature means live in accordance with
your nature what is our nature we cannot
fly like an eagle because flying is not
our teacher
we cannot pounce like a tiger
pouncing is not our nature we can
outstrip like a shark swimming is not
our nature we cannot hop like a kangaroo
hopping is not in our nature so what is
our nature
our nature is we can think we are
rational so when you are not rational
then you are not living according to
nature that's your nature this it also
has another interpretation it's also
nature of the world what is the nature
of the world it's reality okay we
complain about reality all the time
this room is too cold the room is too
warm okay we complain about reality or
you are in Canada and you just go out in
January people complaining about snow I
mean in Toronto in January that's a
reality okay so our life doesn't run
smoothly because we don't live in
accordance with our own nature and with
the nature of reality within the nation
of the world that's the reason why our
life
doesn't run smoothly so if we have to be
sure that we are we live in accordance
with nature if you want to prove to
yourself that how much you contain it
with reality how much you were thinking
is not rational I suggest this exercise
I call that friction finder you can buy
this counter for about six dollars at
Amazon just buy one if not carry a
notebook with you whenever you're
thinking it's not in line with reality
just click on it don't do anything just
click on it whenever you say I should
have done that you start on that what
does it even mean you are fighting
reality if I should have done that no
you can't do that now because today you
should have done that so it contradicts
reality how they're done that I should
whoops I'm late I'm going to be late if
you're going to be late you are going to
be late so you're complaining about
reality or not being rational so do this
exercise for a week and you'll find out
how much of our thinking is irrational
how much overthinking is fighting
rational for our fighting reality now
why do we have this problems why aren't
we aligned with nature destroyed sins it
is your parts that create your
unhappiness people are disturbed by
things that they are not destroyed by
things that happen but by their opinion
of these things you know the way we
think about those things that's what
make us unhappy you may object to that
you may have object to that then say no
Chuck it's not so because I go to a I go
to my annual checkup the doctor gives me
a good report I'm happy that dr. bouche
me a bad report I'm unhappy I go to work
my boss calls me and says you are
promoted that's good news
I'm happy he says you are fired that's
bad news I'm unhappy so what do you mean
by my thoughts create my happiness you
know you want me to be happy when I
imply it do you want me to happy when
you're in bad medical report strikes it
you are really clueless
he says look you are fired yes the
stimulus not the good news you interpret
it as good two people can be fired on
the same day one person might say God
what am I going to do there's a terrible
news you're unhappy the other person
might say Jesus I was coasting on this
job for so long this give me an
opportunity to just take some time off
please think what I want to do and maybe
shape my life it's good that it happened
so it depends on how you interpret it
you may have you may get two people may
get the same with in-court bad medical
report one by it's a god this is
horrible this terrible the other person
might say this is a wake-up call I'm
glad I have time now I can exercise or
do whatever eat properly and do
something better so it's the same thing
the way you look at the world
okay so the impression that's why
impressions are so important it is so
critical in stoicism epictetus said our
said that our most important job is to
test out impressions and accept only
that passed the test and then he went on
to say instead of doing this just this
one thing right
we burden our souls with so many things
that they weigh us down remember that
your only job is to test your
impressions and see whether they pass
the test if you do anything else you are
being yourself down but then like all
great things it is easier to see
difficult to practice so for the next
few minutes we'll be talking about how
we go about practicing this in fact
Viktor Frankl said this between stimulus
and response there is a space in that
space is our power to choose our
response you know a response lies our
growth and our freedom what that means
is this if somebody says something it
appears as an insult to us we
immediately respond by inserting the
person back somebody hits us we
immediately hit them back but what
Viktor Frankl was saying between
something happening and you're
responding there is space you can choose
your response
that's what rationality is to choose
your response okay and you have this
bubble and we give this up because we we
can't even finish for the person to
complete his sentence
we won't interrupt because we don't we
just don't give ourselves space to
respond and this is particularly
critical in our response live a good
life on the road the way you respond
will decide whether you're going to grow
or you're going to stagnate it ended I
need these freedoms
that means we are going to be free or
forever be complaining will depend on
the response you choose so now if you
think if it if you doubt the fact that
you have a choice try this exercise for
a week who doesn't have one of these
everybody has right there carry on
that's you have to have in modern life
everybody has four if you look at that
it has two handles when it's a pull
handle then it's a lift handle so pull
handle you use the pull handle to pull
the back behind you and what that does
is it's very comforting it doesn't
matter how heavy the bag is you can
easily pull it behind you it works
beautifully most of the time but not all
the time if you are walking up the
stairs
will it work it might work but it'll
damage is real see if you pull behind
you when you are walking up the stairs
if it is my tea area will it work no
though it won't so there are times when
you use the other handle you then you
don't use the pull handle you use the
left handle think about it's the same
thing in when we deal with people
suppose you are angry with your friend
it's not working you are angry with that
person and that person is angry with you
it's not working so you're using the
pull handle try the lift handle say this
is not working but after all this person
is my friend and if he did something
stupid so did i I've done so many stupid
things in my life so why be so angry or
even though this was stupid the hundreds
of times he did things that are good
that's reason why he is a friend you
think like this suddenly your anger goes
away and you deal with things
differently
that's where you have the choice you
stop continuing to be angry if you're
angry the other person is angry you are
even more angry that puts even more
angry and this goes on and on and on
use the other handle just the other
handle so every time your life is not
working well you have a choice you have
a choice that's what the strikes in you
have the choice you you can be rational
the rationality is your distinct trait
because which you know what animals have
so how do you do that one other things
you bear to realize is our problem comes
about because we try to control what we
cannot control we try to control what we
cannot control how many of you do this
yes all of us do that we try to control
what we cannot control okay
what's the point in campaigning was know
in January can you control it can you
stop it we cannot stop it we cannot
control it so we make ourselves
miserable by complicated by complaining
about things that are not under control
and if you think what is not under
control you will be amazed
your past is not interior controlled
right you cannot go back and change your
past there's no point in saying oh I had
a bad childhood so big deal you cannot
change it how worrying about what will
happen in your future what what will
happen what happens will happen so your
family is eternity of control well you
can see that your house may be getting
along very well one day she walks out or
he walks out and there's nothing you can
do about it
your family is not everything your
possessions is not trying to control you
your stock market can go down banks can
collapse your lifespan I can live to be
hundred twenty or when I walk how I can
be run over by a car and be dead this
afternoon we don't know that your health
is not under control
what others say or do it's not under can
told you their position is not your
control I cannot control what you think
of me
so in charge whatever is not outside of
your will you don't control so that
means pretty much everything in your
life is not a joke control so when you
try to control what you cannot control
you become anxious you become angry
sometimes you become a slave to somebody
who can tell what they can give you if
you are so attached to a job that you
have to have your job you might do
something unethical to keep your job so
the thing is when you attach to
externals you become anxious angry and
your fault finding you are worried you
become a puppet you become a slave I
suggest you do this exercise for a week
I collect externals element eliminator
is this another may control if not it is
nothing to you what you cannot control
is nothing to you if it snows in January
is it Andre okay don't know it's nothing
to you whatever you cannot control it's
not
think to you if something you had
something bad in the past is nothing to
you whether you are going to live to be
hundred years it's nothing to you but
you're going to strike it rich it's
nothing to you whatever you do not
control is nothing to you practice is
for big what are we don't control is
nothing to you act on what is under your
control this is this is a more important
part it's a very important part of
Stoicism act on what's under your
control most people may say oh I don't
care about what I don't control but
there are sometimes things that are
under your control which you can which
you can act on if we deal with only
those things that we were comfortable no
one can stop you what are the things
going to control things under control or
what you think nobody can I can't
control what you what you think you
control it what you feel nobody can
control it you control it what you feel
what you think nobody can control those
things you control it so you act on what
you control okay don't act on what you
don't control act on what you Lucan
troll if we deal only those things that
are under your control no one can force
you to do anything you don't want to do
no one can stop you you have no enemy no
harm will come to you think about it all
you have to create your happiness is to
ignore what you don't control I'd act on
what you can't control when you do that
you will have no enemy because you are
not complaining about anything that's
not something you control
you are doing just what you can't
control that's all you are doing but
that is enough to create a happy life
that is enough to create a fulfilling
life it is enough to create a life
that's worth living so this exercise is
for a week
action activator
when it is what is under my control act
on what isn't river control act on what
is under control don'ts do not not do
what's under control you lost your job
what is under control you can still
enjoy your meal you can brush up your
resume on LinkedIn you can call it an
employment agency you can do a lot of
things eccentric control but instead why
to ice you know we're getting depressed
that we lost our jobs instead of doing
what what isn't our control act on
what's under your control
don't worry about what's not under your
control yeah so these are the four
foundations of stoic philosophy first
phase happiness is a life that flows
smoothly and our life is not going
smoothly
if anybody alive is flowing smoothly
probably you're wasting your time here
with me anyway see life is not going
smoothly
number two the reason why it doesn't
fall smoothly is we don't act according
to nature
there's accounting to our nature
according to the nature of the world we
are constantly in conflict with our own
nature with the dash of the world that's
the reason why our life is not working
properly and to make it work properly
you have to stop controlling things that
you cannot control and act on what you
can control are you happy
that's twice ism you know one okay but
we're not done yet because we we know
the foundation but you can't live in a
foundation right we we need a house we
can't live on a foundation so we have
the walls wait a window straight have a
roof so what wants the four walls the
foolish walls are there are four special
skills you would need they are also
called for excellences how they are also
called virtues for virtues for
excellences the four walls okay
this these four walls are this you have
to be able to answer four questions you
know all this you know the foundation
the first questions you have to answer
is what to do what not to do at any
given condition what you should do what
you should not do that's number one
question number two who does it belong
to give every person his or her do take
new everyone they do that's number two
and that is question number three
what's question number three what to
select
what not to select
and question number four what you should
be afraid of what it should not be
afraid of four questions what to do what
not to do his wisdom to know what to do
what not to do is visit them to know who
does it belong to and give everyone
their due is justice okay to know what
to select and what not to select it's
moderation not going in excess and to
know what you should be afraid of what
you should not be afraid of what is
terrible what's not terrible that is
courage courage okay so these are the
four skills you should have four skills
you should develop to practice joy
system or four virtues as the you know
they used to turn virtue in modern
parlance virtues kind of looks pompous
okay let's say for special skills
this girl said we can call it for
special skills I like the term for
special skills okay let's let me walk
you through this wisdom what to do what
not to do judging things correctly
this we have already seen before because
we do things that are that are under
work control we don't do things that are
not under control okay that is less
wisdom first skill is wisdom
okay so
it changed what is not exchange is not
up to you so you don't you don't
complain about it you can take an
umbrella you can do that so what to do
not complain about rain what not to do
is contain about rain what to do is take
an umbrella there's turbulence when you
are sailing don't complain about the
turbulence it's not a material control
control the sails in that central
control so you always do things you
ignore what is not under your control
do what isn't over control that is
wisdom that's mister
well I go the doctor doctor says I have
cancer in the early stages can I do
anything about it no I already have
cancer so it's nothing to me can I do
anything about it
yes to radiation chemo eat properly and
I'll be cured I'll do that so we ignore
what is not under control do what's
under control that is wisdom this
exercise you can do for a week in fact
you should do for the rest of your life
I call it epic exam Epictetus
examination it tells you it tells you
it's a it is a basis of wisdom what to
do what not to do do what is do what is
under control
do not worry about what's not and our
country this is a central theme of
choices on it's called the dichotomy see
certain things are under your control
don't worry about them certain things
are voluntary control do them okay
okay the second thing is justice who
sister sauce is not this you have to
give everyone their due you know we
think we are all alone but basically you
are connected to your family and your
friends and your country and ultimately
to the world so that means you don't you
do things that are not just good for you
it's good for your family for your
friends for the family for the world at
large that means if our if if the world
is polluted you do something to clean it
up okay anything that all you know it's
not you don't want to grab that belong
to somebody else because ultimately
these things won't make you happy so the
the the the concept of justice the
virtue of justice in storage system is
that we are connected to this world we
are connect to this world because it's
an expanding circle here start with you
and your family and your friends and the
world and everything else
so whenever you have things like greed
and things like coming on there's an
exercise suggested by well some sort of
suggested by Marcus Aurelius this
thought is unnecessary this thought is
destructive it's not even my true
thought I don't know any big lady person
it's unjust so whenever you have
thoughts of greed and grabbing or yeah
it doesn't matter if we pollute it
doesn't matter or I can have ten plastic
bags or whatever think about it and see
this thought is unnecessary this thought
is destructive this don't buy true
thought it's unjust so I call this Fab
Four exercise this is to practice
justice then we have the moderation the
third skill is moderation what to select
what not to select you got this great
buffet how many people can't resist
emptying a whole bowl of chocolates
[Music]
basically what we have is this colorful
we indulge in excess if a glass of wine
is good two glasses better see is even
better but for about five hours six so
what we do is we continue indulging at
some point you become an alcoholic how
about food yeah once the set is good -
it's better see it's even better for
five at some point you become obese
okay whatever is good taking it to the
extreme negates itself okay so you have
to say when to select and not to select
that is the third scale so more is
better it's one of the reasons we do it
why not because I can afford it so you
buy unnecessary things because you can
afford it okay and sometimes we do it
impress others you buy a bigger car
bigger house not because you need a
bigger house or a bigger car
but impresses somebody else and
certainly we also attempted by or mind
painting a positive image you go there
you see a pair of shoes and say what is
beautiful and you can imagine how well
how beautiful you would look at that
pair of shoes or in that dress except
that after six months you don't even you
don't wear it anymore
in fact I've seen people who would open
the hood a walk-in closet and say I
don't have anything to wear I walk in
and I will look at it and say it's
buzzing with clothes about 300 dresses
and they don't have anything to me you
know the best mind keeps painting a
positive image so we indulge in excess
for various reasons so to get away from
it exercise suggests this exercise pause
and ponder with the pleasure lost yeah I
think this test will make me feel good
but will they do so three months from
now six months from now or will I be
looking for another another dress will
charm me or others if you become an
alcoholic it not only harms you but it
haunts your family so will it Tommy or
others it's not just you or others am i
doing it for approval am i doing it
improve is impress others
and then the the final skill that you
would need is courage courage is
understanding what is terrible and what
is not terrible
okay what is terrible and what's not
sure what you should be afraid of
it's terrible you should be afraid of
not terrible you should not be afraid of
its death terrible this this is terrible
it's old age terrible what is terrible
what is terrible to you anything
terrible well for most people this is
terrible poverty is terrible death is
terrible but stoic say no they are
terrible they are a reality not whatever
this reality is not terrible poverty
disease that is not terrible you don't
control it
what is terrible is your faulty
judgments that's terrible you control it
so what is terrible and what's not
terrible comes from your judgment not
from out there not from with them
poverty is not terrible that is not
terrible this is it's not terrible not
that you would invite it not invited not
that you should relish it it's just if
it happens it's not terrible you can
still be happy
the reason why we do that is we act as
though we are helpless but we have
resources to cope anything that comes
our way let's assume let me assume the
average age of people here older younger
maybe 35 years suppose it is 35 years
you live 35 years facing all the
problems you faced they're going to
repeat again so if you faced it so far
you'll be able to face it in the future
but we say so you ask yourself if this
happens to have any resource to cope
with this the line a supermarket is long
or long itself complaining about they
say what resources you have to cope with
it your patience we can be patient you
have something you are doing something
that is hard we have any strength took
what was think we have what you chose to
do we have to cope with it
you have endurance somebody is abusing
you and you have no way out what string
to have your mental strength so you have
resources to cope with anything that
happens in your life anything
once you realize that then you don't you
don't complain about what might happen
in the future whatever happens happens
because you have the strength to cope
with it okay so these are the four
virtues or four things four special
skills so to review the foundation is
happiness is a life that flows smoothly
our life is not working properly because
our thoughts prevent us from doing that
and to and to make our life work
properly we should ignore what we don't
control act on what we do control try to
make this happen
we should you apply four skills skill
number one what to do what not to do
skill number two
whose is this truth is not this skill
number three what to select what not to
select skill number four what to be
afraid of what not to be afraid of
yeah so those are the four skills now we
have our foundation we have our walls
we need windows right okay what are the
three windows these are three
disciplines you need to practice
discipline a percent discipline of
action and discipline of desire okay
discipline of ascent is every time you
are sent to something suppose you you
know impression is somebody insulted you
you react only if we say yes he inserted
me that's the ascent many times the
impressions are wrong we we are too
strict resent we just say okay that's a
way somebody could be for example you
have a new employee in your office you
try to greet that person try to talk to
him a bit non-communicative you think
it's maybe it's a bit arrogant but maybe
is just shy you are sensitive you are
sent to the impression that is arrogant
but it may just be shy okay so that's a
discipline of ascent before ascending to
something before agreeing to something
see is this true examine your
impressions that is the discipline of
ascent okay yes or no first window
discipline of ascent
number two discipline a faction you know
when you practice justice
it means you act that is if somebody is
hungry give the person food if your
environment is polluted do something to
clean it up it's all action you know
whatever you do outside of you it's an
action that is that is when you practice
justice your practice to the discipline
of action on the third window it's a
discipline of desire when to say yes
wait to say no so these are the three
disciplines you need to practice toy
system
finally we come to the roof what's the
room huh this roof is sloping in two
directions what are those two directions
if you look at it now you have the skill
you have the foundation you have the
skill you're the discipline you may have
the foundation you may have the skill
you may have the discipline still when
you come to daily practice you might
forget to practice right we all do that
we all know the theory but what you
practice every day stays with you if you
don't practice it weakens right so you
have to practice every day how do you
practice every day
one way of doing it is to create what
are known as strike slogans the slogans
would be something like I'm not going to
stop the rain by campaigning so every
time something that's out of control
it's not under your control think of the
old song I'm not going to drop this
chain by complaining then suddenly you
realize yeah you are time to do
something that you cannot control or I
can say oh that handle didn't work room
by the to handle exercise that you might
say oh that title didn't work so halfway
through you are angry or upset and they
or that handle it work so you change
your mindset or it could be oh there's
another pothole my love is rising or
running smoothly so you make up
something whatever appeals to you does
it have to be these so if it is humorous
it's better so immediately see the
absurdity of your thinking will change
and the final second part of the roof is
this you want to enjoy your life so far
we made it work properly but you also
have to enjoy your life you know now you
are writing in the highway of life
there's no potholes there's no traffic
lights it's you're gliding smoothly you
might actually enjoy the scenery right
whether you are driving it's beautiful
outside
epic Taylor said why not enjoy the
festival of five life when it is given
to you to do so it's given to us
above all Lucilius learn to feel the joy
learn to feel the joy that's not the
Stoics same now I know you are what you
are thinking where is this vegetable of
life is happening why ever why wasn't I
in right injury I know you're all
thinking yeah where's the pain right it
if it's happening where is it happening
well it's happening right here right now
okay you know Marcus Aurelius was an
emperor undestroyed
and he ruled an empire that the biggest
the world has ever seen a Patil that
point the biggest the world has ever
seen
so he was the most powerful man in the
world he could have had anything he
wanted what gave him pleasure this what
is this you know when you bake the bread
on the cross streets open traction bread
that was the pleasure figs spreading
open the beauty of a ripe fruit drive
brains building down eyebrows of a lion
so everything that you see is beauty
that's what he said so you are here with
hundred strikes and then 50 strikes it's
not good and our people speaking what
you want to hear maybe maybe not me but
others again so it's that beautiful and
you can afford to come here and listen
to this you can take time off for the
day isn't that beautiful
isn't that wonderful so if you look
around you'll see life is full of joy
okay new young strong the great jazz
musician he sang a song what a wonderful
world he wasn't talking about his
million dollars for his fame but I'm a
flourish moving blue skies white sky
white clouds bright this dark nice
rainbow colors friends beating each
other children growing up so everything
you have if you look around it's a
wonderful world this world is a mirror
of infinite beauty yet no one sees it it
is a temple of majesty yet no one
regards that also by a 17th century boy
this world is a mirror of infinite
beauty yet no one sees it it is a temple
of majesty yet no one regards him so how
do you see it how do you regard it most
of the time we are busy we are busy
living our life to see the beauty of it
so one of the things you can do is do
morning meditation morning meditation
you don't even have to sit cross-legged
and do something when you're lying in
bed before getting up think about the
things you have to be grateful for just
you are awake you should be grateful
right and you have a whole day in front
of here to be grateful I mean you got
friends here to be grateful they got a
family are to be grateful have so many
things to be grateful for just think
about this before getting up yet for a
few minutes think what you should be
grateful for think about what you should
be cheerful about and then prepare for
the day you might find people who are
terrible to you may insult you how are
you going to deal with them just prepare
and then go about there and at the end
of the day you might have forget forgot
most of those things and then review the
day and see what I've done anything
better
[Music]
so that is the house of Stoics a
smoothly flowing life recognizing
thoughts create our unhappiness ignoring
what we cannot control acting on what's
under control using wisdom justice
moderation and courage practicing
discipline fasting desire and action
living our everyday life carefully and
they joined the festival of life okay
that is that is stoicism you know
awfully something funny is happening to
me whenever I feel sad whenever I feel
upset whenever I'm angry whenever
whenever I am irritated I find somebody
following me and laughing laughing at me
behind my back I get this distinct
feeling so I stop and then look back as
the person gets closer I find he's
actually an old man and then it comes
still closer actually I find it's my old
friend
Epictetus you know I say yo epictetus
you have been friends with me for so
long now I feel down and you're laughing
at me and he says Chuck I know you are
not very smart
so I also do just one thing judge your
impressions correctly if you had done
that thing right you wouldn't be angry
or upset and you couldn't do manage one
thing right and you expect me not to
laugh anyway you know if you get angry
if you get irritated if you get upset if
you get annoyed if you think life is
passing you by if you think you are not
enjoying the festival of life look over
your left shoulder look over your left
shoulder maybe an old man is following
you too maybe his name is epictetus
maybe he's telling you do this one thing
right
manage your impressions if we do just
just one thing right you'll never be sad
angry or
say you'll rifle run smoothly this my
friends oh so this world is a mirror of
infinite beauty see it it's a temple of
majesty regarding it is a festival of
life enjoy it above all learn to feel
the joy this my friends is how to be
asteroid when you don't know how thank
you
[Applause]